Finding Aid for Board of Regents (University of Michigan) Records 1817-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Board of Regents (University of Michigan) records
1817-2011
1899-1988
University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
The University of Michigan's highest governing body is the Board of Regents. The Regents deal with virtually every aspect of university policy and campus life. The records of the Regents reflect this broad range of interests and authority. This record group contains exhibits from meetings beginning in 1899. These exhibits are the most complete record of the actions of the Regents, supplementing and detailing the published minutes Proceedings of the Board of Regents. Additional documentation in this record group includes manuscript minutes, 1837-1870, correspondence, material by and about the Regents, photographs, audio recordings of meetings, 1977-2004, and material on recent presidential searches.
8722 Bimu B2 2
185 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
20 oversize items
296.6 MB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group (Donor no. 5932 ) was originally drawn from different University of Michigan administrative offices, mainly the Secretary's Office and the President's Office. Additions are received on an ongoing basis directly from the Board of Regents.
The collection is open for research.
Audiotape recordings of Regents meetings
The Regents of the University of Michigan trace their authority to the founding of the "Catholepistemiad, or University, of Michigania," a body created by Michigan territorial law on August 26, 1817. The Catholepistemiad was to have 13 didaxiim who both served as professors and also formed the governing body of the institution. The "didactors" exercised complete control over the school's affairs and were granted a mandate to establish courses of instruction throughout the territory.
In accordance with the law, acting territorial governor William Woodbridge appointed two men, the Reverends John Monteith and Gabriel Richard, didactors. While the two made a modest beginning, the Catholepistemiad proved far more ambitious a program than the territory was capable of sustaining. Recognizing this fact, a new territorial law was enacted on April 30, 1821, superseding the act of 1817.
The law of 1821 substantially changed the structure of the university's governing body. Control of the "University of Michigan" was removed from the faculty and vested in a board of 21 individuals, "The Trustees of the University of Michigan." The territorial governor served as an ex-officio member of the Trustees, the other members were appointed by and served at the pleasure of the territorial legislature. The law of 1821, like that of 1817, envisioned an institution too large for the territory to successfully support. By 1827 the university no longer offered classes and the building erected in Detroit by the Trustees was being leased to private educational groups.
The state constitution of 1835 recognized implicitly the existence of a state university and granted power to regulate such an institution to the Legislature. No action was taken, however, to revive the dormant university until the passage of a new organic act by the Legislature on March 18, 1837. The law of 1837 re-established "The University of Michigan" and vested its governance in a body called the Board of Regents. The Regents consisted of 12 individuals chosen by the governor with the advice and consent of the state senate, to be presided over by the chancellor (senior administrative officer) of the university, who was made an ex-officio member of the Regents. Other ex-officio members included the governor, the Lt. governor, the judges of the State Supreme Court and the chancellor of the State. The authority of the Regents, in contrast to that of the State Legislature, was unclear. Specifically it was uncertain if the Regents' authority extended to the appointment of a university chancellor, new professorships or selection of branch sites, or if the Legislature's advice and consent was necessary before such actions were legal.
As part of a general revision of Michigan statutes in 1846 the Legislature attempted to define more precisely the exact relationship between itself and the Regents. The Regents were given specifically the power to appoint the university's chancellor and other changes were also made. The result, however, was not particularly helpful in clarifying the overall scope of the Regents' authority.
The state constitution of 1850 proved a watershed in defining the relationship between the Regents and the Legislature. The drafters of the new constitution wished to remove the Regents from the direct political pressure of the Legislature. They therefore established the Regents as a quasi-independent agency. The body was granted the authority to carry out "the general supervision of the University...." The Regents were to be elected to six-year terms of office, each regent being chosen from the state's judicial districts. In 1862 the latter constitutional provision was modified in that Regents were to be elected statewide, and their terms of office were to be staggered, so that two of the eight seats were filled every two years.
While the scope of the "general supervision" clause was not immediately clear, a series of judicial interpretations eventually made it the basis for a broad mandate of authority, limiting the State Legislature's direct interference in university affairs. The State Supreme Court first limited the Legislature in favor of the Regents in the People v. The Regents of the University of Michigan, decided in 1856. The process of judicial interpretation was slow, however, and it was not until 1896 in the case of Sterling v. The Regents of the University of Michigan that the State Supreme Court definitively ruled that the "general supervision" clause of the 1850 constitution barred direct interference by the Legislature in the affairs of the university.
The state constitution of 1908 repeated the "general supervision" clause of the constitution of 1850 while significantly broadening the powers of the Regents. The new document granted the Regents "direction and control of all expenditures from the University funds." The Regents interpreted this clause as granting them the power to dispose of state appropriations without review by state executive officials. The Regents' interpretation of the clause was sustained by the State Supreme Court in 1911 in Board of Regents of the University of Michigan v. The Auditor General. In that case the Court ruled that appropriations to the university became the "property" of the Regents, subject only to such conditions as the Legislature attached to the appropriations.
The Legislature's ability to attach such conditions was limited by the Supreme Court in 1924. Ruling in State Board of Agriculture v. The Auditor General (the constitution of 1908 had granted to Michigan State College, now Michigan State University, and its governing body, the State Board of Agriculture, powers similar to that exercised by the Regents of the University of Michigan), the Court stated that the Legislature could not establish "unconstitutional conditions" to appropriations and that, should the Legislature feel its will violated or ignored by the Regents, its recourse was through the courts. While the decision gave the Regents considerable authority, neither in this decision nor in a number of subsequent rulings, did the State Supreme Court systematically define "unconstitutional provisions," preferring to resolve issues on the merits of the particular case rather than through constitutional interpretation.
The authority granted the Regents by the courts was subtly diminished through subsequent action of the Legislature. In 1933 the Legislature abandoned the historic practice of levying a special mill tax to support the university. Henceforth money was to come from the state's general fund. The possibility for legislative intervention was further enhanced by the decision in 1947 to modify the nature of the university's appropriation from a continuing resolution to an annual one.
While the 1963 state constitution reconfirmed the constitutional status of the Regents as defined in 1850 and 1908, it made changes in the Regents' membership and procedures, while continuing the trend toward increased financial accountability to the Legislature. The constitution of 1963 removed the Superintendent of Public Instruction as an ex-officio member of the Regents. It mandated that all formal sessions of the Regents be opened to the public. Finally it required that an annual accounting of all income and expenditures be made to the Legislature.
In addition to these provisions the 1963 constitution established a state Board of Education and declared it "the general planning and coordinating body for all public education, including higher education." The Regents argued that subsequent clauses of the 1963 constitution limited the Board from impinging upon the traditional powers of the Regents. The Board of Education challenged this interpretation of the constitution, and eventually the issue was placed before the State Supreme Court. That body resolved the issue in favor of the Regents.
A complete List of University of Michigan Regents is available at the Bentley Library web site at http://bentley.umich.edu/exhibits/regents/index.php
Summary Contents List
Fundamental Documents Records of State-University Relations [box 1] Records of Predecessor Institutions [box 1] Laws and Bylaws and Select Proceedings of the Regents [box 1]
Exhibits of Regents Meetings 1899-1910 [boxes 1-5] 1911-1920 [boxes 5-14] 1921-1930 [boxes 14-26] 1931-1941 [boxes 26-44] 1942-1951 [boxes 48-66] 1952-1960 [boxes 74-91] 1961-1965 [boxes 93-105] 1966-1967 [boxes 112-118] 1968-1976 [boxes 121-140] 1977-1980 [boxes 143-150] 1981 [boxes 153-154] 1982 [boxes 155-157] 1983 [boxes 157-160] 1984 [boxes 160, 162-163] 1985-1987 [boxes 163-172] 1985-1987 [boxes 182-185]
Topical Files 1817-1970 (bulk 1867-1928 [boxes 44-47] 1949-1970 [boxes 67-68,] ca. 1976-1982 [box 108] ca. 1958-1999 [boxes 175-181]
Presidential Search Records 1988 [boxes 110-111] 1995-1996 [boxes 141-142]
Correspondence Regents' Correspondence (alphabetical), 1961-1973 [box 68] Regents' Correspondence (chronological), 1963-1973 [boxes 68, 106-107]
Visual Material Photos and portraits [box 92, 142, 174]
Recordings of Regents Meetings Recordings of Regents' Meetings, 1977-2011 [boxes 69-73b, 109, 119-120, 151-152, 161,173]
As the official governing body of the university, the Regents deal with virtually every aspect of university policy and life. The records of the Regents reflect this broad range of interests and authority. But while the documentation is wide-ranging, it is not continuous. Certain types of records are continually before the Regents, particularly information regarding salaries, leaves of absence, appointments to faculty positions, and formal approval of degrees conferred upon students. More often, however, the Regents are presented with a specific problem and asked to resolve it through the creation of policy. After the creation and successful implementation of a policy, the situation which caused the issue to arise is usually no longer a matter of Regental concern. The Regents' records reflect this pattern of action. Issues arise, are resolved, and then are supplanted by new concerns.
The records of the Regents are divided into three series: Fundamental Documents, Exhibits of Regents' Meetings, Materials By and About Regents, Recordings of the Regents' Meetings, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Association for the Promotion of Female Education.; Catholepistemiad (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit Classical Academy.; Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Felch, Alpheus, 1804-1896.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Jenner, William Le Baron, 1832-1907.; Kersey, Jonathan, 1786-1859.; Rose, Preston Benjamin, 1834-1912.; South College (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Administration.Administration.; University of Michigan. Board of Trustees.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Finance.Finance.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Medical School.; University of Michigan--Lands.Lands.; University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.; University of Michigan--Regulations.Regulations.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Gores, Walter J., d. 1966.; Hildebrandi, Herbert W.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Commencements.Commencements.; University of Michigan--Flags.Flags.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Fundamental Documents by or about the University Governing Body
  The first series of the Regents' records contains Fundamental Documents By or About the University Governing Body, including information regarding the predecessors of the Board of Regents. Included are acts of the Michigan territorial and state legislatures which created or modified the university, as well as relevant decisions of the state Supreme Court. Documents from predecessor bodies include the minutes of the Trustees of the University of Michigan (1821-37) and the Detroit Classical Academy (1818-29). Selected Regents' material found in this series include the minutes of the Regents' Executive Committee (1845-57) and manuscript minutes of Regents' meetings (1837-70).
  - Records of State-University Relations
    - Act establishing Catholespistemiad or University of Michigania (photostatic copy), 1817 (Box 1)
    - Act establishing the University of Michigan and various Territorial laws, 1837 (Box 1)
    - Constitutional and Statutory provisions re University, compiled, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Record of Legislative acts re University, 1817-1911 (Box 1)
    - Decisions of State Supreme Court (undated) (Box 1)
    - Opinion of Constitutional status of Regents written by Alpheus Felch, 1850 (Box 1)
  - Records of Predecessor Institutions
    - Laws of the University, 1817-1818 (Box 1)
    - Minutes Detroit Classical Academy, 1818-1829 (Box 1)
    - Minutes Trustees of the University of Michigan, 1821-1837
      - Manuscript (Box 1)
      - Photostatic copy, 1 oversize volumes (Box 1)
      - Typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Laws and By-laws and Select Records of the Regents
    - University laws, 1883-1914; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Tentative by-laws of Regents, drawn up by Lucius L. Hubbard, 1920 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, Regents Executive Committee, 1845-1851; 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Proceedings of the Regents
      - 1837-1854, 1 oversize volumes (Box 1)
      - 1855-1870, 1 oversize volumes (Box 1)
- Exhibits of the Regents Meetings, 1899-1987
  The Exhibits of Regents' Meetings series (1899-1975, 1996-2000) includes various items: correspondence, reports, recommendations, and other documents presented to the Regents for consideration at their meetings. In addition to these files, the researcher should note that the Bentley Historical Library maintains a complete set of the Regents' printed official minutes. Proceedings of the Board of Regents began in 1837 and continues to the present. These proceedings are extensively indexed and may be located through the printed catalog. The published proceedings include many of the items within the Exhibit series. The majority of exhibits, however, are merely alluded to in the minutes. Thus, this series is the most complete record of the actions of the Board of Regents. To speed retrieval exhibits filed after August 1908 were identified by a letter. As the number of exhibits expanded beyond the letters of the alphabet, the practice became to label the exhibit following "Z" as "AA." Similarly, the exhibit following "ZZ" was designated "AAA." The practice of writing out all of the letters was abandoned in 1928 and supplanted by a shorthand notation. Exhibit "AA" was designated "A2," and "AAA" as "A3."
  Exhibit letters do not appear in the official printed Regents' minutes. They are, however, included in the draft minutes and the agendas which precede each meeting's exhibits. Since the Secretary prepared both the agenda and the exhibits, exhibits usually were taken up sequentially, but exceptions to this rule are common.
  Exhibits regarding trust funds were systematically removed from the files and placed in a special location. Such removals were noted by the insertion of a printed form. The trust fund file has not yet been transferred to the archives.
  Note: More recent materials from the meetings (from March 1996 to present), including detailed agendas, exhibit material, and reports on finances, promotions, and degree confirmation, are available in the record group University of Michigan. Board of Regents Agendas.
  - 1899-1910
    - February 16, 1899 (Box 1)
    - March 2(?), 1899 (Box 1)
    - April 25, 1899 (Box 1)
    - May 11, 1899 (Box 1)
    - June 20, 1899 (Box 1)
    - July 26, 1899 (Box 1)
    - September 20, 1899 (Box 1)
    - October 11, 1899 (Box 1)
    - November 17, 1899 (Box 1)
    - December 13, 1899 (Box 1)
    - January 17, 1900 (Box 2)
    - February 14, 1900 (Box 2)
    - March 14, 1900 (Box 2)
    - April 18, 1900 (Box 2)
    - May 17, 1900 (Box 2)
    - June 19, 1900 (Box 2)
    - July 18, 1900 (Box 2)
    - September 5, 1900 (Box 2)
    - October 17, 1900 (Box 2)
    - November 27, 1900 (Box 2)
    - December 21, 1900 (Box 2)
    - January 17, 1901 (Box 2)
    - February 21, 1901 (Box 2)
    - May 16, 1901 (Box 2)
    - June 7, 1901 (Box 2)
    - July 10, 1901 (Box 2)
    - August 2, 1901 (Box 2)
    - October 16, 1901 (Box 2)
    - November 26, 1901 (Box 2)
    - December 20, 1901 (Box 2)
    - January 24, 1902 (Box 2)
    - February 27, 1902 (Box 2)
    - March 14, 1902 (Box 2)
    - April 23, 1902 (Box 2)
    - May 15, 1902 (Box 2)
    - June 17(?), 1902 (Box 2)
    - July 17, 1902 (Box 2)
    - September 10, 1902 (Box 2)
    - November 21, 1902 (Box 2)
    - December 19, 1902 (Box 2)
    - January 9, 1903 (Box 2)
    - March 5, 1903 (Box 2)
    - April 22, 1903 (Box 2)
    - May 14, 1903 (Box 2)
    - June 16, 1903 (Box 2)
    - July 16, 1903 (Box 2)
    - September 9, 1903 (Box 2)
    - October 14, 1903 (Box 2)
    - November 24, 1903 (Box 2)
    - December 22, 1903 (Box 2)
    - January 14, 1904 (Box 2)
    - February 12, 1904 (Box 2)
    - March 11, 1904 (Box 2)
    - April 14, 1904 (Box 2)
    - May 11, 1904 (Box 2)
    - June 21, 1904 (Box 2)
    - July 20, 1904 (Box 2)
    - September 22, 1904 (Box 2)
    - October 13, 1904 (Box 2)
    - November 11, 1904 (Box 2)
    - December 27, 1904 (Box 2)
    - January 20, 1905 (Box 2)
    - February 16, 1905 (Box 2)
    - March 20, 1905 (Box 2)
    - April 24, 1905 (Box 2)
    - May 11, 1905 (Box 2)
    - June 20, 1905 (Box 3)
    - July 18, 1905 (Box 3)
    - September 13, 1905 (Box 3)
    - October 11, 1905 (Box 3)
    - November 17, 1905 (Box 3)
    - December 14, 1905 (Box 3)
    - January 19, 1906 (Box 3)
    - February 14, 1906 (Box 3)
    - March 23, 1906 (Box 3)
    - April 24, 1906 (Box 3)
    - May 9, 1906 (Box 3)
    - June 19, 1906 (Box 3)
    - July 25, 1906 (Box 3)
    - September 25, 1906 (Box 3)
    - October 26, 1906 (Box 3)
    - November 14, 1906 (Box 3)
    - December 8, 1906 (Box 3)
    - January 18, 1907
      - Regents Meeting (Box 3)
      - Petition of Charles H. Myers to Regents (Box 3)
    - February 21, 1907 (Box 3)
    - March 22, 1907 (Box 3)
    - April 19, 1907 (Box 3)
    - May 8, 1907 (Box 3)
    - June 13, 1907 (Box 3)
    - June 18-20, 1907 (Box 3)
    - June 28, 1907 (Box 3)
    - September 25, 1907 (Box 3)
    - October 18, 1907 (Box 3)
    - November 15, 1907 (Box 3)
    - December 13, 1907 (Box 3)
    - January 15, 1908 (Box 3)
    - February 19, 1908 (Box 3)
    - March 20, 1908 (Box 3)
    - April 24, 1908 (Box 3)
    - May 22, 1908 (Box 3)
    - June 5, 1908 (Box 3)
    - June 16, 1908 (Box 3)
    - July 14, 1908 (Box 3)
    - September 24, 1908 (Box 3)
    - October 21, 1908 (Box 4)
    - November 13, 1908 (Box 4)
    - December 11, 1908 (Box 4)
    - January 11, 1909 (Box 4)
    - February 17, 1909 (Box 4)
    - March 24, 1909 (Box 4)
    - April 28, 1909 (Box 4)
    - May 12, 1909 (Box 4)
    - June 4, 1909 (Box 4)
    - June 22, 1909 (Box 4)
    - July 8, 1909 (Box 4)
    - September 28, 1909 (Box 4)
    - November 4, 1909 (Box 4)
    - December 3, 1909 (Box 4)
    - January 7, 1910 (Box 4)
    - February 9, 1910 (Box 4)
    - March 4, 1910 (Box 4)
    - April 15, 1910 (Box 4)
    - May 25, 1910 (Box 4)
    - June 8, 1910 (Box 4)
    - June 28, 1910 (Box 5)
    - July 21, 1910 (Box 5)
    - October 7, 1910 (Box 5)
    - November 18, 1910
      - Draft Minutes and A-F (Box 5)
      - G-MMM (Box 5)
    - December 21, 1910 (Box 5)
  - 1911-1920
    - January 11, 1911 (Box 5)
    - February 23, 1911 (Box 5)
    - March 23, 1911 (Box 5)
    - April 14, 1911 (Box 5)
    - May 25, 1911 (Box 5)
    - June 27, 1911
      - Draft Minutes and A-F (Box 5)
      - G-MMM (Box 5)
    - July 20, 1911
      - Draft Minutes and A (Box 5)
      - B-HH (Box 5)
    - September 28, 1911 (Box 5)
    - October 26, 1911 (Box 5)
    - November 17, 1911 (Box 6)
    - December 15, 1911 (Box 6)
    - January 26, 1912
      - Draft Minutes and A (Box 6)
      - A 1/2-L (Box 6)
    - February 29, 1912
      - Draft Minutes and A-I (Box 6)
      - J-GGG (Box 6)
    - March 22, 1912 (Box 6)
    - April 25, 1912 (Box 6)
    - May 24, 1912 (Box 6)
    - June 24, 1912
      - Draft Minutes and A-B (Box 6)
      - C-KKK (Box 6)
    - July 18, 1912
      - Draft Minutes (Box 6)
      - A-RR (Box 6)
    - September 27, 1912
      - Draft Minutes and A-B (Box 6)
      - C-PPP (Box 6)
    - October 25, 1912 (Box 6)
    - November 15, 1912 (Box 7)
      - Draft Minutes and A-I (Box 7)
      - J-TT (Box 7)
    - January 17, 1913
      - Draft Minutes and A-N (Box 7)
      - P-TTT (Box 7)
    - February 17-18, 1913 (Box 7)
    - March 25, 1913 (Box 7)
    - April 24, 1913
      - Draft Minutes and A-T (Box 7)
      - U-GGG (Box 7)
    - May 29, 1913 (Box 7)
    - June 24, 1913
      - Draft Minutes and A-Z (Box 7)
      - AA-VV (Box 7)
    - July 18, 1913
      - Draft Minutes (Box 7)
      - A-XX (Box 7)
      - Appendices re: estimated fire loss, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - October 3, 1913
      - Draft Minutes and A-E (Box 7)
      - F-PPP (Box 7)
    - November 14, 1913
      - Draft Minutes and A-L (Box 8)
      - M-BBB (Box 8)
    - December 19, 1913 (Box 8)
    - January 27, 1914
      - Draft Minutes and A-J (Box 8)
      - K-AAA (Box 8)
    - February 17, 1914 (Box 8)
    - March 27, 1914 (Box 8)
    - April 29, 1914 (Box 8)
    - May 22, 1914 (Box 8)
    - June 23, 1914 (Box 8)
    - July 24, 1914 (Box 8)
    - October 15 and 16, 1914 (Box 8)
    - November 24, 1914
      - Draft Minutes and A-L (Box 8)
      - M-CCC (Box 8)
    - December 22, 1914 (Box 8)
    - January 21, 1915 (Box 9)
    - February 10, 1915 (Box 9)
    - March 25, 1915 (Box 9)
    - April 22, 1915 (Box 9)
    - May 21, 1915 (Box 9)
    - June 3, 1915 (Box 9)
    - June 22, 1915
      - Draft Minutes and A-X (Box 9)